<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | TJ VanToll]]></title>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-25T22:47:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://tjvantoll.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TJ VanToll]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tj.vantoll@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Detecting Internet Explorer without jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2013/01/11/detecting-internet-explorer-without-jquery/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-11T17:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2013/01/11/detecting-internet-explorer-without-jquery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the changes in jQuery's <a href="http://blog.jquery.com/2013/01/09/jquery-1-9-rc1-and-migrate-rc1-released/">upcoming 1.9 release</a> is the removal of <a href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.browser/">$.browser</a>.  So if you're using it to test for Internet Explorer, what do you do?</p>

<h3>Option 1: Use the migrate plugin</h3>

<p>If you want to avoid upgrading existing code, use the <a href="https://github.com/jquery/jquery-migrate/">migrate plugin</a> which will preserve <code>$.browser</code> as it was.  Of course this is simply putting off the inevitable, but if you need to upgrade a large code base it's a good temporary measure.  The development version of the plugin will produce a console warning message whenever <code>$.browser</code> is used, which can help you identify where you're using it and migrate accordingly.</p>

<h3>Option 2: Switch to feature detection</h3>

<p>Testing for specific browsers is <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/why-browser-sniffing-stinks/">a</a> <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/hh475813.aspx">bad</a> <a href="http://diveintohtml5.info/detect.html">practice</a>.  If you are not supporting IE because of features that it does not possess, test for those features instead of the browser.  The <a href="http://modernizr.com">Modernizr</a> library includes a wide variety of feature tests and is a good place to get started.</p>

<h3>Option 3: Use conditional classes or conditional comments</h3>

<p>IE versions &lt;= 10 support <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms537512(v=vs.85).aspx">conditional comments</a> that can be used to detect Internet Explorer.  For example the <a href="http://html5boilerplate.com/">HTML5 boilerplate</a> <a href="https://github.com/h5bp/html5-boilerplate/blob/master/index.html">uses the following</a> to show a warning to users using IE &lt; 7:</p>

<p>``` html</p>

<!--[if lt IE 7]>
    <p class="chromeframe">
        You are using an <strong>outdated</strong> browser. Please
        <a href="http://browsehappy.com/">upgrade your browser</a>
        or <a href="http://www.google.com/chromeframe/?redirect=true">
        activate Google Chrome Frame</a> to improve your experience.
    </p>
<![endif]-->


<p>```</p>

<p>This approach can be used to add conditional classes on the <code>html</code> element (<a href="http://paulirish.com/2008/conditional-stylesheets-vs-css-hacks-answer-neither/">via Paul Irish</a>).</p>

<p>``` html Conditional classes on the html element</p>

<!--[if lt IE 7]>      <html class="ie6"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if IE 7]>         <html class="ie7"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if IE 8]>         <html class="ie8"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if gt IE 8]><!-->


<p> <html>         <!--<![endif]-->
```</p>

<p>Now the presence of a class on the <code>html</code> element can be used to derive the version of Internet Explorer the user is using:</p>

<p><code>javascript
$('html').hasClass('ie6'); //True if the user is using IE6
</code></p>

<h3>Option 4: Sniff the User Agent</h3>

<p>If for whatever reason you cannot do any of the options above, you <em>can</em> determine IE usage the from <code>navigator</code> object.</p>

<div class="warning" style="display: block;">
    User agent sniffing should be used as a last resort.  Make sure you at least consider the options above before using this.
</div>


<p>``` javascript Sniffing the user agent string to test for Internet Explorer
//Test for Internet Explorer
if (/MSIE\s([\d.]+)/.test(navigator.userAgent)) {</p>

<pre><code>//Get the IE version.  This will be 6 for IE6, 7 for IE7, etc...
version = new Number(RegExp.$1);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[maxlength Constraint Validation Oddities in Major Browsers]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T12:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <code>maxlength</code> attribute has been around in browsers for a long time.  When provided all browsers prevent the user entering a value that exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>For example you cannot type more than 2 characters in the textbox below:</p>

<p><input type="text" maxlength="2" /></p>

<h3>Constraint Validation</h3>

<p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/HTML5/Constraint_validation_">Constraint validation</a> is an HTML5 spec that provides native client side form validation in the browser.  As part of its <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/Forms_in_HTML#Constraint_Validation_API">API</a>, all <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;textarea&gt;</code> elements have a <code>validity.tooLong</code> property that is <code>true</code> when the length of the <code>value</code> exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>But if the browser prevents this then why does the property exist?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Prefilled value Attribute</h3>

<p>Assume that you're filling the <code>value</code> of form elements with information from a database and you end up with something like this:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC" /&gt;</code></p>

<p>How will the browser handle this?</p>

<p>All browsers will prevent entry of additional characters, but they do not trim excess characters already present.  Additionally all browsers will allow a form containing the above input to submit.  <em>Note: Opera is the only browser to set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> in this situation.  Despite this, it does not prevent form submission.</em></p>

<p>Why is submission not prevented?  The key is in the <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">specification</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Constraint validation: If an element has a maximum allowed value length, its dirty value flag is true, its value was last changed by a user edit (as opposed to a change made by a script), and the code-unit length of the element's value is greater than the element's maximum allowed value length, then the element is suffering from being too long.</p></blockquote>

<p>The <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">dirty flag</a> essentially means the the user has changed the value of an element.  Therefore, in order to be <code>tooLong</code> the element must have been last interacted with by a user edit.</p>

<h3>Actually Triggering tooLong</h3>

<p>So let's take another approach.  What happens if you have the same input:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC" /&gt;</code></p>

<p>...remove one character, then submit?  You can try it for yourself below:</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 180px;" src="http://jsfiddle.net/tj_vantoll/epCQe/embedded/result,html/" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>Upon edit IE10 and Chrome will set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> and prevent form submission.  If the user attempts to submit a form after removing the "C" they will see the following in those browsers:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/Chrome.png" title="Chrome" alt="Chrome" />
<img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/IE10.png" title="IE10" alt="IE10" /></p>

<p>Firefox, Safari, and Opera incorrectly handle this situation and allow the form to be submitted anyways.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using jQuery UI's Slider to Polyfill HTML5's input[type=range]]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/09/14/using-jquery-ui-slider-to-polyfill-html5-input-type-range/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-14T21:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/09/14/using-jquery-ui-slider-to-polyfill-html5-input-type-range</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://jqueryui.com/demos/slider">jQuery UI's slider plugin</a> looks and behaves much like the browser's native <code>input[type=range]</code> control; therefore it makes an excellent choice for <a href="http://remysharp.com/2010/10/08/what-is-a-polyfill/">polyfilling</a> the native behavior.</p>

<h3>How to do it</h3>

<p>The main issue is that the slider must be built on a block level node, not an <code>&lt;input&gt;</code>.  Therefore you must create another container node (in this case a <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>) to create the slider from then hide the original <code>&lt;input&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>Here's the script that I used.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>``` javascript Polyfill input[type=range] with jQuery UI's Slider
$(function() {</p>

<pre><code>//Determine whether the browser natively supports input[type=range].
//If you're using Modernizr this is equivalent to Modernizr.inputtypes.range
var input = document.createElement('input');
input.setAttribute('type', 'range');
var rangeSupport = input.type != 'text';

if (!rangeSupport) {
    var $input, $slider;

    $('input[type=range]').each(function(index, input) {
        $input = $(input);

        //Create a new div, turn it into a slider, and set its attributes based on
        //the attributes of the input.  If the input doesn't possess those attributes
        //use jQuery UI's defaults.
        $slider = $('&lt;div /&gt;').slider({
            min: parseInt($input.attr('min'), 10) || 0,
            max: parseInt($input.attr('max'), 10) || 100,
            value: parseInt($input.attr('value'), 10) || 0,
            step: parseInt($input.attr('step'), 10) || 1,
            slide: function(event, ui) {
                //Keep the value of the input[type=range] in sync with the slider.
                $(this).prev('input').val(ui.value);
            }
        });

        //Append the slider after the input and hide the input.  The user will only
        //interact with the slider.        
        $input.after($slider).hide();
    });
}
</code></pre>

<p>});
```</p>

<h3>Future</h3>

<p>This approach handles the most common use cases but it isn't perfect.  For example, if you want to disable the <code>&lt;input type="range"&gt;</code> you'll have to disable the slider as well.</p>

<p>There is a <a href="http://bugs.jqueryui.com/ticket/5800">feature request to add support for this natively in the slider plugin</a> itself, but it's been sitting inactive for quite some time now.  Hopefully over time <code>input[type=range]</code> support will become ubiquitous enough that we can drop these workarounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTML5 Form Validation - Start Using it in Production Applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/30/html5-form-validation-start-using-it-in-production-applications/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/30/html5-form-validation-start-using-it-in-production-applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Forms suck, yet, they make or break the most crucial online transactions.  Building web forms sucks as well; the APIs and lack of customizability has confused and frustrated people for years.  As a byproduct an abundance of horribly unusable forms have been created for everyone to suffer through.</p>

<p>Therefore <em>anything</em> that makes this process easier should be greeted with joy and enthusiasm.</p>

<p>HTML5 does just this by including a built in <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/Forms_in_HTML#Constraint_Validation_API">client side form validation mechanism</a> designed to make implementing client side validation powerful, seamless, and most importantly - easy to implement.</p>

<p>Great!  Despite this, HTML5 form validation is a topic relegated to presentations and demos; I personally have yet to fill out a web form in the wild that actually makes use of it.</p>

<p>Why?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Browser Support</h3>

<p>One reason people avoid HTML5 form validation is lack (or perceived lack) of browser support for the new APIs.  However the <a href="http://caniuse.com/#feat=form-validation">list of supported browsers</a> now includes the latest version of every major browser, including:</p>

<ul>
<li>IE 10</li>
<li>Firefox 4+</li>
<li>Chrome 10+</li>
<li>Safari 5+</li>
<li>Opera 10+</li>
<li>Opera Mobile</li>
<li>Chrome for Android</li>
<li>Firefox for Android</li>
</ul>


<h3>What to do in unsupported browsers?</h3>

<p>This is <em>the</em> problem.  Despite browser support being relatively good, for most sites there are still going to be a substantial amount of users with browsers that simply do not support the new APIs.  Therefore, if you are intending to support these users you have to start forking your code to support both browsers with native support and browsers without it.</p>

<p>While this can absolutely be done, it's time consuming and a bit of a nuisance.  It's faster and easier to simply ditch the native validation and use your own.  In this case you don't have to worry about multiple code paths; every user in every browser will hit the same codepath and get the same experience.</p>

<h3>What if we did nothing?</h3>

<p>But what if we took a new approach to this problem - simply don't do client side validation in unsupported browsers, at all.  This is advantageous for a number of reasons.</p>

<p>1) <strong>No dual maintenance</strong>.  One thing that has always bothered me about doing validation on both the client and server side is that you're validating the #1 principle of software development - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't_repeat_yourself"><strong>D</strong>on't <strong>R</strong>epeat <strong>Y</strong>ourself</a>.</p>

<p>2) <strong>No dependencies</strong>.  If you only use native browser APIs to provide client side validation you don't have to worry about maintaining plugin or library dependencies that might not be maintained.</p>

<p>3) <strong>Faster and easier</strong>.  The browser APIs are simple and easy to use.  Want to make a field required?  <a href="http://wufoo.com/html5/attributes/09-required.html">Add the <code>required</code> attribute</a>.  Want to make a field only accept email address?  <a href="http://wufoo.com/html5/types/1-email.html">Add <code>type=email</code> to your <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> field</a>.</p>

<p>4) <strong>Future Friendly</strong>.  Although currently a number of older browsers (namely IE &lt;= 9) do not support the new APIs, eventually they all will.  Therefore, eventually all users will hit the client side validation as intended.</p>

<h3>But, you can't just not validate data... right?</h3>

<p>Of course you have to validate client submitted data, but you already need to be doing that on the server side anyways.  What this approach requires you to do is simply return formatted error messages from your server side processing and <a href="http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2011/11/08/extensive-guide-web-form-usability/">display them in a usability friendly way</a>.  You're likely doing that already.</p>

<h3>What About Polyfills?</h3>

<p><a href="http://remysharp.com/2010/10/08/what-is-a-polyfill/">Polyfills</a> are great and a number of <a href="https://github.com/Modernizr/Modernizr/wiki/HTML5-Cross-browser-Polyfills">HTML5 form validation polyfills</a> exist.  My problem with polyfills in this case is that they add a dependency that I believe is unnecessary.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>HTML5 provides native solutions to validating client side data and most all modern browsers support it.  Yet, most people are still relying on the JavaScript hacks we've been using for well over a decade now.</p>

<p>It's time.  Come to the dark side.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Analytics - Excluding Your Own Visits in Development and Production]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/28/google-analytics-excluding-visits-in-development-and-production/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/28/google-analytics-excluding-visits-in-development-and-production</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Googling how to exclude your own <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> traffic returns a plethora of results, however, nearly all of them advocate 1 of 2 approaches:</p>

<ul>
<li>Creating an IP filter in Google Analytics itself <a href="http://support.google.com/analytics/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=1034840&amp;rd=1">(example)</a>.</li>
<li>Creating a page that sets a cookie which tells Google Analytics to exclude the traffic <a href="http://webmasters.stackexchange.com/questions/15552/how-do-you-exclude-yourself-from-google-analytics-on-your-website-using-cookies">(example)</a>.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Problems</h3>

<p>These approaches are silly in my opinion.  IP addresses change.  In fact, most ISPs change subscriber's IP addresses quite regularly.  Furthermore, most people visit their site on a wide variety of devices in a wide variety of places.  Maintaining a list of IP addresses in Google Analytics would be a nightmare.</p>

<p>The cookie approach works, but it is a pain to have to create and maintain the page that sets the cookie.  It's also problematic because verifying whether the cookie is actually active is difficult.  Do you know where your browser stores your cookies and how to access them?  How about your smart phone?  Because of this you end up constantly having to create the cookie before accessing the site, which is a nuisance.</p>

<h3>JavaScript</h3>

<p>Both these approaches seem especially silly considering how easy it is to simply accomplish this with JavaScript.  You can simply check for the exclusion criteria before including the Google Analytics code snippet.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Excluding localhost Traffic</h3>

<p>If you test your site on a local server you likely don't want that traffic being logged.  Assuming that your local server is using <code>localhost</code> as the hostname the following will exclude the traffic.</p>

<p>``` javascript Excluding localhost Traffic</p>

<script>
    if (window.location.host != 'localhost') {
        var _gaq = _gaq || [];
        _gaq.push(['_setAccount', 'UA-12345678-1']);
        _gaq.push(['_trackPageview']);

        (function() {
            var ga = document.createElement('script'); ga.type = 'text/javascript'; ga.async = true;
            ga.src = ('https:' == document.location.protocol ? 'https://ssl' : 'http://www') + '.google-analytics.com/ga.js';
            var s = document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0]; s.parentNode.insertBefore(ga, s);
        })();
    }
</script>


<p>```</p>

<h3>Excluding Production Traffic</h3>

<p>While the above works great during development it won't help you when you're accessing your site on its live production server.  For that I would suggest using a request parameter.</p>

<p>For example if your site is <code>http://mysite.com</code> then you could visit <code>http://mysite.com?analytics=off</code> to exclude the logging.  The following script makes it so that any page view with the appropriate <code>analytics=off</code> request parameter is not logged.</p>

<p>``` javascript Excluding Production Traffic via a Request Parameter</p>

<script>
    var useAnalytics = true;

    try {
        //Turn off analytics if 'analytics=off' is included as a request parameter.
        var parameters = window.location.search.split('&');
        if (parameters[0]) {
            parameters[0] = parameters[0].replace('?', '');
        }
        for (var i = 0; i < parameters.length; i++) {
            var values = parameters[i].split('=');
            if (values[0] == 'analytics' && values[1] == 'off') {
                useAnalytics = false;
            }
        }
    } catch(e) {
        //Just in case something goes wrong...
        useAnalytics = true;
    }

    if (useAnalytics) {
        var _gaq = _gaq || [];
        _gaq.push(['_setAccount', 'UA-12345678-1']);
        _gaq.push(['_trackPageview']);

        (function() {
            var ga = document.createElement('script'); ga.type = 'text/javascript'; ga.async = true;
            ga.src = ('https:' == document.location.protocol ? 'https://ssl' : 'http://www') + '.google-analytics.com/ga.js';
            var s = document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0]; s.parentNode.insertBefore(ga, s);
        })();
    }
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>With this approach you could simply create a bookmark with the request parameter in the URL and use that to access the site.</p>

<p>Furthermore, it would be easy to add on code to <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/DOM/document.cookie">set a cookie</a> or utilize <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/DOM/Storage#localStorage">localStorage</a> to save the preference so you don't have to always include the request parameter.</p>

<h3>Combining the Approaches</h3>

<p>In case you want to include both of these here's a code snippet that makes it so that both <code>localhost</code> traffic and pages with a <code>analytics=off</code> request parameter are excluded.</p>

<p>``` javascript The Final Exclusion Script</p>

<script>
    var useAnalytics = true;

    try {
        //Turn off analytics if 'analytics=off' is included as a request parameter.
        var parameters = window.location.search.split('&');
        if (parameters[0]) {
            parameters[0] = parameters[0].replace('?', '');
        }
        for (var i = 0; i < parameters.length; i++) {
            var values = parameters[i].split('=');
            if (values[0] == 'analytics' && values[1] == 'off') {
                useAnalytics = false;
            }
        }

        //Turn off analytics if 'localhost' is the host
        if (window.location.host == 'localhost') {
            useAnalytics = false;
        }
    } catch(e) {
        //Just in case something goes wrong...
        useAnalytics = true;
    }

    if (useAnalytics) {
        var _gaq = _gaq || [];
        _gaq.push(['_setAccount', 'UA-29179796-1']);
        _gaq.push(['_trackPageview']);

        (function() {
            var ga = document.createElement('script'); ga.type = 'text/javascript'; ga.async = true;
            ga.src = ('https:' == document.location.protocol ? 'https://ssl' : 'http://www') + '.google-analytics.com/ga.js';
            var s = document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0]; s.parentNode.insertBefore(ga, s);
        })();
    }
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>If you have any other recommendations for how to exclude Google Analytics traffic let me know in the comments.</p>

<h3>Update (January 1st, 2013)</h3>

<p>Reader Aaron Hillyer has created a WordPress plugin to implement the request parameter exclusion approach, <a href="http://socialmediabar.com/enhanced-google-analytics-tracking">check it out</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
