<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | TJ VanToll]]></title>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-23T23:29:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tjvantoll.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TJ VanToll]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tj.vantoll@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better Ways of Comparing a JavaScript String to Multiple Values]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2013/03/14/better-ways-of-comparing-a-javascript-string-to-multiple-values/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2013/03/14/better-ways-of-comparing-a-javascript-string-to-multiple-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a seemingly simple programming task that we deal with everyday.  Here's the situation:</p>

<ul>
<li>1) You have a string in JavaScript, like <code>var fruit = ''</code>.</li>
<li>2) You need to know if that string is equal to one of multiple values, say <code>"banana"</code> or <code>"lemon"</code> (because the yellow fruits need special yellow fruit processing or something).</li>
</ul>


<p>Most people accomplish this by doing two string comparisons connected by a logical OR, which looks like this:</p>

<p>``` javascript
if (fruit == 'banana' || fruit == 'lemon') {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Which works fine, but is a bit clunky.  I mean, you have to type <code>fruit ==</code> two whole times.  It also doesn't scale well.  Say your fruit processing product takes off and you need to support more fruit, now you have this:</p>

<p>``` javascript
if (fruit == 'banana' || fruit == 'lemon' || fruit == 'mango' || fruit == 'pineapple') {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This is getting a bit ugly.  Let's look at some other ways of accomplishing the same check.</p>

<h3>Switch</h3>

<p>The switch statement can be used to achieve the same ends:</p>

<p>``` javascript
switch (fruit) {</p>

<pre><code>case 'banana':
case 'lemon':
case 'mango':
case 'pineapple':
    handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This approach would be helpful if we have to handle for multiple classifications of fruits.  But for one check it's a lot of typing and takes up a lot of space.</p>

<h3>Array Based</h3>

<p>ECMAScript 5 introduced an <code>indexOf</code> method on <code>Array.prototype</code> (<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Array/indexOf">docs</a>).  We can use this to create an array on the fly, then see whether the value matches one of the values in the array:</p>

<p>```javascript
if (['banana', 'lemon', 'mango', 'pineapple'].indexOf(fruit) >= 0) {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This is better, but still not ideal.  Understanding this code relies on the reader knowing that the <code>indexOf</code> method returns <code>-1</code>, which is not necessarily common knowledge.</p>

<p>Also, because <code>Array.prototype.indexOf</code> was added in ECMAScript 5, it's not present in IE &lt;= 8.  Therefore, if you're supporting IE &lt;= 8, you either need to add an <code>indexOf</code> method to the prototype yourself or use a library.</p>

<p>Speaking of libraries, most provide a cross browser means of finding values in an array.</p>

<h4>jQuery</h4>

<p><a href="http://jquery.com">jQuery</a> provides an <code>inArray</code> method (<a href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.inArray/">docs</a>):</p>

<p>``` javascript
if ($.inArray(fruit, ['banana', 'lemon', 'mango', 'pineapple']) >= 0) {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h4>Underscore</h4>

<p><a href="http://underscorejs.org">Underscore.js</a> provides a <code>contains</code> method (<a href="http://underscorejs.org/#contains">docs</a>):</p>

<p>``` javascript
if (_.contains(['banana', 'lemon', 'mango', 'pineapple'], fruit)) {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Other libraries provide similar methods.  Personally, I find Underscore's API to be the cleanest.  The contains API intuitively returns a boolean and there's not much to type.  You might however find yourself needing to remember the order of the parameters (does the array come first or the value?).</p>

<p>The check would be cleaner if the <code>contains</code> method were added to <code>Array.prototype</code> directly:</p>

<p>``` javascript
Array.prototype.contains = function(obj) {</p>

<pre><code>return this.indexOf(obj) &gt; -1;
</code></pre>

<p>};
```</p>

<p>This allows the check to be:</p>

<p>``` javascript
if (['banana', 'lemon', 'mango', 'pineapple'].contains(fruit)) {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h3>Regular Expressions</h3>

<p>An often overlooked means of performing this check is to use regular expressions via <code>String.prototype.match</code> (<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/String">docs</a>).</p>

<p>``` javascript
if (fruit.match(/<sup>(banana|lemon|mango|pineapple)$/))</sup> {</p>

<pre><code>handleYellowFruit();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This check clearly requires the least amount of typing.  It is also the most flexible as you can easily alter things like case sensitivity, special character handling, white space, etc.  This will work in all browsers and you don't have to worry about messing with the native prototypes.</p>

<p>While this is the most powerful option, it comes at a cost of being less readable.  I had to look up the <code>^</code> (match at the beginning of input) and <code>$</code> (match at the end of input) characters when writing this post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Detecting Internet Explorer without jQuery]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2013/01/11/detecting-internet-explorer-without-jquery/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-11T17:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2013/01/11/detecting-internet-explorer-without-jquery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the changes in jQuery's <a href="http://blog.jquery.com/2013/01/09/jquery-1-9-rc1-and-migrate-rc1-released/">upcoming 1.9 release</a> is the removal of <a href="http://api.jquery.com/jQuery.browser/">$.browser</a>.  So if you're using it to test for Internet Explorer, what do you do?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Option 1: Use the migrate plugin</h3>

<p>If you want to avoid upgrading existing code, use the <a href="https://github.com/jquery/jquery-migrate/">migrate plugin</a> which will preserve <code>$.browser</code> as it was.  Of course this is simply putting off the inevitable, but if you need to upgrade a large code base it's a good temporary measure.  The development version of the plugin will produce a console warning message whenever <code>$.browser</code> is used, which can help you identify where you're using it and migrate accordingly.</p>

<h3>Option 2: Switch to feature detection</h3>

<p>Testing for specific browsers is <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/why-browser-sniffing-stinks/">a</a> <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/hh475813.aspx">bad</a> <a href="http://diveintohtml5.info/detect.html">practice</a>.  If you are not supporting IE because of features that it does not possess, test for those features instead of the browser.  The <a href="http://modernizr.com">Modernizr</a> library includes a wide variety of feature tests and is a good place to get started.</p>

<h3>Option 3: Use conditional classes or conditional comments</h3>

<p>IE versions &lt; 10 support <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms537512(v=vs.85).aspx">conditional comments</a> that can be used to detect Internet Explorer.  For example the <a href="http://html5boilerplate.com/">HTML5 boilerplate</a> <a href="https://github.com/h5bp/html5-boilerplate/blob/master/index.html">uses the following</a> to show a warning to users using IE &lt; 7:</p>

<p>``` html</p>

<!--[if lt IE 7]>
    <p class="chromeframe">
        You are using an <strong>outdated</strong> browser. Please
        <a href="http://browsehappy.com/">upgrade your browser</a>
        or <a href="http://www.google.com/chromeframe/?redirect=true">
        activate Google Chrome Frame</a> to improve your experience.
    </p>
<![endif]-->


<p>```</p>

<p>This approach can be used to add conditional classes on the <code>html</code> element (<a href="http://paulirish.com/2008/conditional-stylesheets-vs-css-hacks-answer-neither/">via Paul Irish</a>).</p>

<p>``` html Conditional classes on the html element</p>

<!--[if lt IE 7]>      <html class="ie6"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if IE 7]>         <html class="ie7"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if IE 8]>         <html class="ie8"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if gt IE 8]><!-->


<p> <html>         <!--<![endif]-->
```</p>

<p>Now the presence of a class on the <code>html</code> element can be used to derive the version of Internet Explorer the user is using:</p>

<p><code>javascript
$('html').hasClass('ie6'); //True if the user is using IE6
</code></p>

<h3>Option 4: Sniff the User Agent</h3>

<p>If for whatever reason you cannot do any of the options above, you <em>can</em> determine IE usage the from <code>navigator</code> object.</p>

<div class="warning" style="display: block;">
    User agent sniffing should be used as a last resort.  Make sure you at least consider the options above before using this.
</div>


<p>``` javascript Sniffing the user agent string to test for Internet Explorer
//Test for Internet Explorer
if (/MSIE\s([\d.]+)/.test(navigator.userAgent)) {</p>

<pre><code>//Get the IE version.  This will be 6 for IE6, 7 for IE7, etc...
version = new Number(RegExp.$1);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[maxlength Constraint Validation Oddities in Major Browsers]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T12:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <code>maxlength</code> attribute has been around in browsers for a long time.  When provided, all browsers prevent the user entering a value that exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>For example you cannot type more than 2 characters in the textbox below:</p>

<p><input type="text" maxlength="2"></p>

<h3>Constraint Validation</h3>

<p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/HTML5/Constraint_validation_">Constraint validation</a> is an HTML5 spec that provides native client side form validation in the browser.  As part of its <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/Forms_in_HTML#Constraint_Validation_API">API</a>, all <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;textarea&gt;</code> elements have a <code>validity.tooLong</code> property that is <code>true</code> when the length of the <code>value</code> exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>But if the browser prevents this, then why does the property exist?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Prefilled value Attribute</h3>

<p>Assume that you're populating the <code>value</code> of form elements from a database and you end up with something like this:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC"&gt;</code></p>

<p>How will the browser handle this?</p>

<p>All browsers will prevent entry of additional characters, but they do not trim excess characters already present.  Additionally, all browsers will allow a form containing the above input to submit.  <em>Note: Opera is the only browser to set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> in this situation.  Despite this, it does not prevent form submission.</em></p>

<p>Why is submission not prevented?  The key is in the <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">specification</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Constraint validation: If an element has a maximum allowed value length, its dirty value flag is true, its value was last changed by a user edit (as opposed to a change made by a script), and the code-unit length of the element's value is greater than the element's maximum allowed value length, then the element is suffering from being too long.</p></blockquote>

<p>The <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">dirty flag</a> essentially means that the user has changed the value of an element.  Therefore, in order to be <code>tooLong</code>, the element must have been edited.</p>

<h3>Actually Triggering tooLong</h3>

<p>So let's take another approach.  What happens if you have the same input:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC"&gt;</code></p>

<p>...remove one character, then submit?  You can try it for yourself below:</p>

<p><div class="code_example"><h6>Triggering tooLong Errors<a href="/demos/2012-10-17/tooLong.html" target="_blank">Open in New Window</a></h6><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 130px;" frameborder="0" src="/demos/2012-10-17/tooLong.html"></iframe></div></p>

<p>Upon edit IE10 and Chrome will set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> and prevent form submission.  If the user attempts to submit a form after removing the "C" they will see the following in those browsers:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/Chrome.png" title="Chrome" alt="Chrome" />
<img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/IE10.png" title="IE10" alt="IE10" /></p>

<p>Firefox, Safari, and Opera incorrectly handle this situation and allow the form to be submitted anyways.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using jQuery UI's Slider to Polyfill HTML5's input[type=range]]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/09/14/using-jquery-ui-slider-to-polyfill-html5-input-type-range/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-14T21:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/09/14/using-jquery-ui-slider-to-polyfill-html5-input-type-range</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://jqueryui.com/demos/slider">jQuery UI's slider plugin</a> looks and behaves much like the browser's native <code>input[type=range]</code> control; therefore it makes an excellent choice for <a href="http://remysharp.com/2010/10/08/what-is-a-polyfill/">polyfilling</a> the native behavior.</p>

<h3>How to do it</h3>

<p>The main issue is that the slider must be built on a block level node, not an <code>&lt;input&gt;</code>.  Therefore you must create another container node (in this case a <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>) to create the slider from then hide the original <code>&lt;input&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>Here's the script that I used.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>``` javascript Polyfill input[type=range] with jQuery UI's Slider
$(function() {</p>

<pre><code>//Determine whether the browser natively supports input[type=range].
//If you're using Modernizr this is equivalent to Modernizr.inputtypes.range
var input = document.createElement('input');
input.setAttribute('type', 'range');
var rangeSupport = input.type != 'text';

if (!rangeSupport) {
    var $input, $slider;

    $('input[type=range]').each(function(index, input) {
        $input = $(input);

        //Create a new div, turn it into a slider, and set its attributes based on
        //the attributes of the input.  If the input doesn't possess those attributes
        //use jQuery UI's defaults.
        $slider = $('&lt;div /&gt;').slider({
            min: parseInt($input.attr('min'), 10) || 0,
            max: parseInt($input.attr('max'), 10) || 100,
            value: parseInt($input.attr('value'), 10) || 0,
            step: parseInt($input.attr('step'), 10) || 1,
            slide: function(event, ui) {
                //Keep the value of the input[type=range] in sync with the slider.
                $(this).prev('input').val(ui.value);
            }
        });

        //Append the slider after the input and hide the input.  The user will only
        //interact with the slider.        
        $input.after($slider).hide();
    });
}
</code></pre>

<p>});
```</p>

<h3>Future</h3>

<p>This approach handles the most common use cases but it isn't perfect.  For example, if you want to disable the <code>&lt;input type="range"&gt;</code> you'll have to disable the slider as well.</p>

<p>There is a <a href="http://bugs.jqueryui.com/ticket/5800">feature request to add support for this natively in the slider plugin</a> itself, but it's been sitting inactive for quite some time now.  Hopefully over time <code>input[type=range]</code> support will become ubiquitous enough that we can drop these workarounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTML5 Form Validation - Start Using it in Production Applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/30/html5-form-validation-start-using-it-in-production-applications/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/08/30/html5-form-validation-start-using-it-in-production-applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Forms suck, yet, they make or break the most crucial online transactions.  Building web forms sucks as well; the APIs and lack of customizability has confused and frustrated people for years.  As a byproduct an abundance of horribly unusable forms have been created for everyone to suffer through.</p>

<p>Therefore <em>anything</em> that makes this process easier should be greeted with joy and enthusiasm.</p>

<p>HTML5 does just this by including a built in <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/Forms_in_HTML#Constraint_Validation_API">client side form validation mechanism</a> designed to make implementing client side validation powerful, seamless, and most importantly - easy to implement.</p>

<p>Great!  Despite this, HTML5 form validation is a topic relegated to presentations and demos; I personally have yet to fill out a web form in the wild that actually makes use of it.</p>

<p>Why?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Browser Support</h3>

<p>One reason people avoid HTML5 form validation is lack (or perceived lack) of browser support for the new APIs.  However the <a href="http://caniuse.com/#feat=form-validation">list of supported browsers</a> now includes the latest version of every major browser, including:</p>

<ul>
<li>IE 10</li>
<li>Firefox 4+</li>
<li>Chrome 10+</li>
<li>Safari 5+</li>
<li>Opera 10+</li>
<li>Opera Mobile</li>
<li>Chrome for Android</li>
<li>Firefox for Android</li>
</ul>


<h3>What to do in unsupported browsers?</h3>

<p>This is <em>the</em> problem.  Despite browser support being relatively good, for most sites there are still going to be a substantial amount of users with browsers that simply do not support the new APIs.  Therefore, if you are intending to support these users you have to start forking your code to support both browsers with native support and browsers without it.</p>

<p>While this can absolutely be done, it's time consuming and a bit of a nuisance.  It's faster and easier to simply ditch the native validation and use your own.  In this case you don't have to worry about multiple code paths; every user in every browser will hit the same codepath and get the same experience.</p>

<h3>What if we did nothing?</h3>

<p>But what if we took a new approach to this problem - simply don't do client side validation in unsupported browsers, at all.  This is advantageous for a number of reasons.</p>

<p>1) <strong>No dual maintenance</strong>.  One thing that has always bothered me about doing validation on both the client and server side is that you're validating the #1 principle of software development - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't_repeat_yourself"><strong>D</strong>on't <strong>R</strong>epeat <strong>Y</strong>ourself</a>.</p>

<p>2) <strong>No dependencies</strong>.  If you only use native browser APIs to provide client side validation you don't have to worry about maintaining plugin or library dependencies that might not be maintained.</p>

<p>3) <strong>Faster and easier</strong>.  The browser APIs are simple and easy to use.  Want to make a field required?  <a href="http://wufoo.com/html5/attributes/09-required.html">Add the <code>required</code> attribute</a>.  Want to make a field only accept email address?  <a href="http://wufoo.com/html5/types/1-email.html">Add <code>type=email</code> to your <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> field</a>.</p>

<p>4) <strong>Future Friendly</strong>.  Although currently a number of older browsers (namely IE &lt;= 9) do not support the new APIs, eventually they all will.  Therefore, eventually all users will hit the client side validation as intended.</p>

<h3>But, you can't just not validate data... right?</h3>

<p>Of course you have to validate client submitted data, but you already need to be doing that on the server side anyways.  What this approach requires you to do is simply return formatted error messages from your server side processing and <a href="http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2011/11/08/extensive-guide-web-form-usability/">display them in a usability friendly way</a>.  You're likely doing that already.</p>

<h3>What About Polyfills?</h3>

<p><a href="http://remysharp.com/2010/10/08/what-is-a-polyfill/">Polyfills</a> are great and a number of <a href="https://github.com/Modernizr/Modernizr/wiki/HTML5-Cross-browser-Polyfills">HTML5 form validation polyfills</a> exist.  My problem with polyfills in this case is that they add a dependency that I believe is unnecessary.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>HTML5 provides native solutions to validating client side data and most all modern browsers support it.  Yet, most people are still relying on the JavaScript hacks we've been using for well over a decade now.</p>

<p>It's time.  Come to the dark side.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
