<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: CSS | TJ VanToll]]></title>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/blog/categories/css/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-25T22:20:11-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tjvantoll.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TJ VanToll]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tj.vantoll@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Default Browser Handling of the CSS text-transform Property]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/07/10/default-browser-handling-of-the-css-text-transform-property/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-10T21:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/07/10/default-browser-handling-of-the-css-text-transform-property</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <code>text-transform</code> CSS property is most frequently used to uppercase and lowercase text.  According to the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/text.html#caps-prop">CSS 2.1 specification</a> it is also an inherited property, meaning, when no value is specified on a given element, it should inherit its parent's <code>text-transform</code> value.</p>

<p>If no parents have a <code>text-transform</code> property defined, the element will take on the default value of <code>none</code>.</p>

<p>Where it gets interesting is that all browsers define default <code>text-transform</code> properties for certain form elements.  What does this mean?  <!--more-->Let's say you have the following markup:</p>

<p>``` html</p>





<div>
    <input type="text" value="foo" />
    <input type="submit" value="bar" />
</div>


<p>```</p>

<p>Both <code>foo</code> and <code>bar</code> will appear lowercased in all major browsers.  You can see this for yourself below:</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="http://jsfiddle.net/tj_vantoll/DxANv/1/embedded/result,html,css/" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>This happens because all browser vendors include <code>text-transform: none</code> in their user agent stylesheet for those elements.  Therefore the <code>text-transform: uppercase</code> rule declared on the parent node is not inherited.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, but not surprisingly, browsers are not consistent about their default values for all elements.</p>

<h3>What the Browsers Do</h3>

<p>The following chart shows popular browser rendering engines and whether their user agent stylesheet includes <code>text-transform: none</code> for the listed elements.</p>

<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>Rendering Engine</th>
            <th>input[type=submit]</th>
            <th>input[type=text]</th>
            <th>select</th>
            <th>textarea</th>
            <th>button</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td>Trident (Internet Explorer)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><strong>No</strong></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Gecko (Firefox)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><strong>No</strong></td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><strong>No</strong></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>WebKit (Chrome, Safari, etc...)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Presto (Opera)</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><strong>No</strong></td>
            <td>Yes</td>
            <td><strong>No</strong></td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>


<p>The rendering engines that have a <strong>No</strong> for a given element declare no default for <code>text-transform</code>.  Therefore, those elements will inherit the value from their parent.</p>

<h3>What Does This Mean?</h3>

<p>The browser differences occur on the <code>button</code> and <code>select</code> elements.  Therefore, if you apply a <code>text-transform</code> value to a node, AND that node has children <code>button</code> / <code>select</code> nodes, AND you do not apply a <code>text-transform</code> value to the <code>button</code> or <code>select</code> nodes themselves... you'll get different behavior in different browsers.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<p>``` html
&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html></p>

<pre><code>&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;style&gt;
        form { text-transform: uppercase; }
    &lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;form&gt;
        &lt;!-- "foo" will be uppercase in IE, Firefox, and Opera --&gt;
        &lt;!-- "foo" will be lowercase in WebKit based browsers --&gt;
        &lt;button&gt;foo&lt;/button&gt;

        &lt;!-- "bar" will be uppercase in Firefox and Opera --&gt;
        &lt;!-- "bar" will be lowercase in IE and WebKit based browsers --&gt;
        &lt;select&gt;
            &lt;option&gt;bar&lt;/option&gt;
        &lt;/select&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<h3>Consistency</h3>

<p>You could make arguments as to whether the user agent stylesheets <em>should</em> be defaulting the <code>text-transform</code> of various form elements to <code>none</code>, but to most people all that matters is that the behavior is consistent.  It's easy enough to override the defaults if you don't like them.</p>

<p>Therefore to get consistent behavior you would <em>think</em> you would need to set the default value of <code>button</code> and <code>select</code> elements to either <code>none</code> or <code>inherit</code>.</p>

<p>``` css
/<em> Option 1 - Don't inherit values in all browsers </em>/
button, select { text-transform: none; }</p>

<p>/<em> Option 2 - Inherit values in all browsers </em>/
button, select { text-transform: inherit; }
```</p>

<p>But unfortunately for whatever reason Option 2 doesn't work on the <code>&lt;select&gt;</code> in IE &lt;= 7, Safari, and most interestingly, doesn't take effect in Chrome until you click on <code>&lt;select&gt;</code>.  You can verify this behavior for yourself below:</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="http://jsfiddle.net/tj_vantoll/dUjXB/10/embedded/result,html,css/" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>Fortunately Option 1 does indeed produce the same behavior in IE6+, Firefox, Chrome, Safari, and Opera.  Therefore to normalize <code>text-transform</code> you need to include the following in your stylesheet.</p>

<p><code>css Cross Browser text-transform Goodness
button, select { text-transform: none; }
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ideal LESS Workflow with git]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/07/07/the-ideal-less-workflow-with-git/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/07/07/the-ideal-less-workflow-with-git</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>LESS is a CSS pre-processor written in JavaScript.  Unlike its main competitor SASS, it has the ability to run both on the client side via a simple <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tag, as well as server-side in Node.js.  The fact that LESS files can be processed client side is advantageous for a number of reasons:</p>

<h4><strong>There are no dependencies.</strong></h4>

<p>To develop LESS files all you need is your browser.  SASS requires Ruby to be running on your system to generate the CSS files.</p>

<p>While some would argue that this isn't a big deal (Ruby is pre-installed on OS X for example), it can potentially put off beginners or those not familiar with the command line.  A lot of people that write CSS wear a designer hat more than a developer hat.  Even if <em>you</em> know what you're doing, if you're on a team with less technical people oftentimes the simplest approach will make everyone happy.</p>

<h4><strong>You can auto-reload changes to less files without reloading the browser and without external dependencies.</strong></h4>

<p>With LESS you can easily watch for changes by appending <code>#!watch</code> to the URL or by running <code>less.watch()</code> from the console.  There's no additional setup and no need to reload your browser, changes take effect automatically.</p>

<p>If you want files to be regenerated using SASS you must tell SASS which files to watch via the command line or use an app that does that for you.  If you want CSS changes to happen without reloading your browser you need to enlist the help of an app / extension such as <a href="http://livereload.com">LiveReload</a>.  While this works fine this is yet another dependency.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Production</h3>

<p>While the ease of use during development is great, you don't want visitors to your site to incur the cost of processing the LESS files client side in a production setting.  The easy way to accomplish this is to manually run <code>lessc</code> from the command line to convert all LESS files into CSS files, and then updating all of your .less paths in <code>&lt;link&gt;</code> tags to use .css paths.</p>

<p>This works, but the lazy programmer in you will be looking to automate this after doing this more than once.  If you're using Git for source control one way you can accomplish this is by running a commit hook to do the generation.</p>

<h3>Git Commit Hooks</h3>

<p><a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Customizing-Git-Git-Hooks">Git commit hooks</a> allow you to run scripts whenever a commit occurs.  A <code>pre-commit</code> hook allows you to run a script that can also optionally prevent the commit from occurring.  The <code>pre-commit</code> hook works well for generating CSS files from LESS files for a few reasons.</p>

<ul>
<li>Once the script is in place you no longer have to manually generate CSS files, it'll simply be done automatically when you commit changes to source control.</li>
<li>The script can be setup so that if <code>lessc</code> fails the commit will be rejected.  Therefore, LESS files with invalid syntax will be kept out of source control.</li>
</ul>


<p>To create a Git commit hook navigate into the <code>.git/hooks</code> directory of your repository.  This folder has a number of sample hooks that you can potentially use with a <code>.sample</code> suffix.  To create a <code>pre-commit</code> script that Git will run simply create an un-prefixed copy of <code>pre-commit.sample</code>.</p>

<p><code>bash
cd /MyProject/.git/hooks
cp pre-commit.sample pre-commit
</code></p>

<p>Once a <code>pre-commit</code> file exists in <code>.git/hooks</code>, Git will run it before every commit.</p>

<h3>The Script</h3>

<p>There are many ways to implement a script that generates CSS files from LESS files.  This is the <code>pre-commit</code> script that I use.</p>

<p>``` bash The script</p>

<h1>!/bin/sh</h1>

<h1>Pre-commit hook to generate .css files from .less files using lessc.</h1>

<h1>Script assumes .less files are in a directory named "less" and will</h1>

<h1>put the generated files in a sibling "css" directory.  The generated</h1>

<h1>CSS will also be compressed as part of lessc.</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>When .less files are deleted the script will delete the corresponding</h1>

<h1>.css files if they exist.</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>Example</h1>

<h1>-------</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>Before:       After:</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>foo/          foo/</h1>

<h1>less/         css/</h1>

<h1>a.less        a.css</h1>

<h1>bar/            less/</h1>

<h1>less/           a.less</h1>

<h1>b.less    bar/</h1>

<h1>css/</h1>

<h1>b.css</h1>

<h1>less</h1>

<h1>b.less</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>Loop over all files included in the commit.</h1>

<p>for file in $( exec git diff-index --cached --name-only HEAD )
do</p>

<h1>We only want to take action unless the file is a LESS file.</h1>

<p>  if [[ $file == <em>".less"</em> ]]; then</p>

<pre><code>lessFile=$file
</code></pre>

<h1>Find where the corresponding CSS file should be located</h1>

<h1>in the file system, in this case a sibling CSS directory.</h1>

<pre><code>cssFile="${lessFile/less\//css/}"
cssFile="${cssFile/.less/.css}"
</code></pre>

<h1>Determine the status of the file in the commit.</h1>

<h1>M = Modified, A = Added, D = deleted, R = renamed,</h1>

<h1>C = copied, U = Updated but unmerged</h1>

<pre><code>status=$( exec git status --porcelain $lessFile )
</code></pre>

<h1>If the file was deleted as part of the commit, delete the</h1>

<h1>corresponding CSS file.</h1>

<pre><code>if [[ $status == D* ]]; then
  if [ -e "$cssFile" ]; then
    echo "Removing $cssFile"
    git rm $cssFile 
  fi
else
</code></pre>

<h1>Otherwise we must generate the CSS file. First create a</h1>

<h1>CSS folder to place the file in.  The -p option for mdkir</h1>

<h1>tells it to create parent folders if necessary.</h1>

<pre><code>  baseDirectory=${lessFile/less\/*/}
  mkdir -p ${baseDirectory}css
</code></pre>

<h1>Log to the console that the CSS is being generated so the person</h1>

<h1>running the commit is aware.</h1>

<pre><code>  echo "Generating $cssFile from $lessFile"
</code></pre>

<h1>Run lessc to do the actual generation.  If lessc fails exit</h1>

<h1>with a code of 1 so that the commit is rejected.  The -x option</h1>

<h1>tells lessc to generate compressed CSS for production usage.</h1>

<pre><code>  if ! lessc -x $lessFile $cssFile; then
    exit 1
  fi
</code></pre>

<h1>Add the CSS file to the commit.</h1>

<pre><code>  git add $cssFile
fi
</code></pre>

<p>  fi
done
```</p>

<p>You could greatly simplify this script to simply run <code>lessc</code> on all .less files on every commit.  I go file by file because the script has to be run on a large code base where generating hundreds to thousands of CSS files on every commit isn't practical.  This script is also setup to create sibling <code>css</code> and <code>less</code> directories.  You could easily modify this to simply put the files in the same directory; I like them to be logically separated.</p>

<h3>Automating <code>&lt;link&gt;</code> File Paths</h3>

<p>As I said, the script I use assumes that there are sibling <code>css</code> and <code>less</code> directories.  To give a concrete example of this say I have the following file system structure.</p>

<pre><code>/MyProject
    /css
        * Generated files *
    index.html
    /js
        less.js
    /less
        a.less
        b.less
</code></pre>

<p>To include these files I use the following locally:</p>

<p>``` html Local Includes</p>

<!-- index.html -->


<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html></p>

<pre><code>&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet/less" href="less/a.less"&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet/less" href="less/b.less"&gt;
    &lt;script src="js/less.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<p>And the following in production:</p>

<p>``` html Production Includes</p>

<!-- index.html -->


<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html></p>

<pre><code>&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="css/a.css"&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="css/b.css"&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<p>The best way to handle both development and production with minimal maintenance is to use some sort of server-side check so that you don't have to change your HTML whenever you release to production.  Here's an example of a PHP script that does this by detecting whether the host contains <code>localhost</code>.</p>

<p>``` html Making both imports work</p>

<!-- index.html -->


<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html></p>

<pre><code>&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;? if (strpos($_SERVER['HTTP_HOST'], 'localhost')) { ?&gt;
        &lt;link rel="stylesheet/less" href="http://tjvantoll.com/less/a.less"&gt;
        &lt;link rel="stylesheet/less" href="http://tjvantoll.com/less/b.less"&gt;
        &lt;script src="http://tjvantoll.com/js/less.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt; } else { ?&gt;
        &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://tjvantoll.com/css/a.css"&gt;
        &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="http://tjvantoll.com/css/b.css"&gt;
    &lt;? } ?&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Using LESS client side is awfully convenient, but it shouldn't be done in a production setting.  If you use LESS a lot then this is something you'll want to automate in your workflow.  In my opinion using a git <code>pre-commit</code> hook is a clean way to accomplish this.  Feel free to use my script or alter it to your liking.  If you have any other ways you automate your LESS workflow I'd love to hear about it.  Let me know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Browser CSS Parsing Discrepancies]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/06/10/browser-css-parsing-discrepancies/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-10T22:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/06/10/browser-css-parsing-discrepancies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Possibly the most frustrating thing that can happen during web development is when things look or behave differently in different browsers for no apparent reason.</p>

<p>One of the major features of HTML5 is a <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/parsing.html">parsing algorithm</a> that specifies not only how to handle well formed markup, but also what to do with invalid HTML.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/syndata.html#parsing-errors">CSS specification</a> actually does the same.  In fact, it goes into explicit detail for how to handle a wide variety of nonsense syntax that it might encounter.  For example...</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Declarations with unkown properties should be ignored.</strong></p>

<p>``` css
h1 { color: red; foo: bar; }</p>

<p>/<em> foo is an unkown property so the browser should interpret this as... </em>/
h1 { color: red; }
```</p>

<p><strong>Illegal values should be ignored.</strong></p>

<p>``` css
h1 { float: 'foo'; }</p>

<p>/<em> foo is an invalid value for the float property and should be ignored </em>/
```</p>

<p>These are just a sampling of what is specified.  The above rules are well documented and consistenly followed by all browsers.  Unfortunately that is not the case as we get into more complicated scenarios.</p>

<h3>Malformed Strings in CSS</h3>

<p>Take a guess, what <em>should</em> happen with the following:</p>

<p>``` html</p>

<div data-number="one">one</div>


<div data-number="two">two</div>


<p>​</p>



<p>```
The relevant portion of the specification states that...</p>

<p><blockquote><p>User agents must close strings upon reaching the end of a line (i.e., before an unescaped line feed, carriage return or form feed character), but then drop the construct (declaration or rule) in which the string was found.</p><footer><strong>CSS Specification</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/syndata.html#parsing-errors'>www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Let's take this one rule at a time.</p>

<pre><code>background: url("some-url);
</code></pre>

<p>Per the spec you would expect the <code>background</code> to be ignored because of the malformed string, and it is in all browsers I tested.</p>

<pre><code>color: red;
</code></pre>

<p>This is kind of in a gray area.  The spec says that the <em>construct in which the unclosed string was found</em> should be dropped, which makes it seem like this rule shouldn't be interpreted.   But what about subsequent rules that were encountered before a new line?  It seems like the browser could be smart enough to apply this rule.</p>

<pre><code>color: blue;
</code></pre>

<p>Per the spec you would expect this to be interpreted since a new line character occurred between the unclosed quote and this rule.</p>

<pre><code>border: 2px solid black;
</code></pre>

<p>Along the same lines you would also expect a border to be around both divs since by then normal parsing of the stylesheet should resume.</p>

<p>Here's what a sampling of browsers actually do.</p>

<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>Browser</th>
            <th>Div one color</th>
            <th>Div two color</th>
            <th>Border around the divs</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td>Chrome 19</td>
            <td class="red">Red</td>
            <td class="blue">Blue</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Safari 5.1.7</td>
            <td class="red">Red</td>
            <td class="blue">Blue</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
        </tr>        
        <tr>
            <td>Firefox 12</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>        
        <tr>
            <td>Opera 11.62</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Opera Mobile</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr> 
        <tr>
            <td>iOS 5</td>
            <td class="red">Red</td>
            <td class="blue">Blue</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
        </tr> 
        <tr>
            <td>Android 2+</td>
            <td class="red">Red</td>
            <td class="blue">Blue</td>
            <td>Yes</td>
        </tr> 
        <tr>
            <td>Internet Explorer 7</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Internet Explorer 8</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Internet Explorer 9</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Internet Explorer 10</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>Black</td>
            <td>No</td>
        </tr>        
    </tbody>
</table>


<p>You can see what your browser does here.</p>

<iframe style="width: 100%; height: 120px;" src="http://jsfiddle.net/tj_vantoll/PHKLz/3/embedded/result,html,css/" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<h3>Results</h3>

<p>WebKit based browsers are evaluating all rules after a semicolon is encountered and all other browsers stop in their tracks and don't evaluate any other rules.  The same results occur with some other common fat finger situations.</p>

<p>``` css
/<em> Notice the mix of single and double quote in the url property value. </em>/
[data-number='one'] { background: url("some_url'); color: red; }
[data-number='two'] { color: blue; }
/<em> In WebKit browsers the color: blue; will be evaluated, in others it will not be. </em>/</p>

<p>/<em> Same thing if there's an malfored selector (notice the missing single quote in the selector. </em>/
[data-number=one'] { color: red; }
[data-number='two'] { color: blue; }
/<em> Again in Webkit color: blue; will be evaluated, in others it will not be. </em>/
```</p>

<h3>What Could Possibly Go Wrong?</h3>

<p>Frankly, since this is an error situtation I don't think many developers would care what the browser does with this.  If the rules aren't evaluated it becomes pretty clear there's an issue and it becomes pretty easy to find and clean up the issue.  What is important to developers is that the results are consistent.  The danger here is if you make a quick fix to a CSS file, fat finger some quotes, and only test in WebKit, you could catastrophically break your styling in non-WebKit browsers.</p>

<h3>Avoiding Issues</h3>

<p>The obvious way to avoid running into issues is to test your code in all browsers.  However, with the number of browsers and devices there are to test on that's not always feasible, especially for trivial changes.</p>

<p>Modern editors with syntax highlighting can help you find malformed strings by creating an obvious syntax highlighting problem.  If yours doesn't you might want to consider switching to one that does.</p>

<p>Furthermore, tools like <a href="http://csslint.net/">CSS Lint</a> can help detect issues <a href="https://github.com/stubbornella/csslint/wiki/IDE-integration">via your editor / IDE</a> or at build time by <a href="https://github.com/stubbornella/csslint/wiki/Command-line-interface">incorporating them into a Node.js or Ant build process</a>.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>While the CSS specification tries to standarize what to do with invalid CSS browsers still handle some situations differently.  Make sure your editor or build process can help detect silly typos, and attempt to test your code in a variety of browsers, even for trivial changes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Styling Disabled Form Fields]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/03/17/Styling-Disabled-Form-Fields/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/03/17/Styling-Disabled-Form-Fields</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Form fields can be disabled by simply adding the <code>disabled</code> attribute.</p>

<p><code>html Simple Disabled Fields
&lt;input type="text" disabled /&gt;
&lt;textarea disabled&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
&lt;select disabled&gt;&lt;/select&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Disabled fields cannot be interacted with by the user; the browser will not allow the field to receive focus or be tabbed to.  For an intuitive UI it's important that disabled fields are clearly evident to the user.  Users are easily confused and frustrated when attempting to interact with fields that they are not able to.</p>

<p>To apply custom styling to disabled fields you can add CSS rules that target <code>input:disabled</code>, <code>select:disabled</code>, &amp; <code>textarea:disabled</code>. (Note: IE doesn't support the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/En/CSS/%3Adisabled">disabled pseduo class</a> until IE9, so you'll need to use <code>input[disabled]</code>, <code>select[disabled]</code>, &amp; <code>textarea[disabled]</code> <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/CSS/Attribute_selectors">attribute selectors</a> if IE &lt; 9 support is important for you.  It'll work just the same.)</p>

<p>While you <i>can</i> provide custom disabled field styling, it's not generally a good idea.  All browsers come with default styling for these fields that attempt to mesh with native UI elements in the OS.  Also, users have a certain expectation for what disabled fields look like in their preferred web browser and it's best not to mess with that.</p>

<p>Unfortunately some browser's default styling is less than ideal.  <!--more-->To best show this I've created a <a href="http://jsfiddle.net/ygwnh/12/">test case</a> with the most common form elements and recorded a rendering of the test case in a large number of browser / OS combinations.  Since some of the styles are more evident when a the element is selected and/or has a value, I included both a grouping with no <code>selected</code> or <code>value</code> attributes, and another with those set.</p>

<h3>Markup</h3>

<p>Here's the markup I used for the test cases, some very basic form fields with the <code>disabled</code> attribute.</p>

<h4>No Value / Selected Attributes</h4>

<p>``` html Markup Used to Generate the Examples http://jsfiddle.net/ygwnh/12/</p>

<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>Enabled</th>
            <th>Disabled</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="text" /></td>
            <td><input type="text" disabled /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="checkbox" /></td>
            <td><input type="checkbox" disabled /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="radio" /></td>
            <td><input type="radio" disabled /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><select></select></td>
            <td><select disabled></select></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><textarea></textarea></td>
            <td><textarea disabled></textarea></td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>


<p>```</p>

<h4>With Value / Selected Attributes</h4>

<p>``` html Markup Used to Generate the Examples http://jsfiddle.net/ygwnh/12/</p>

<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>Enabled w/Value</th>
            <th>Disabled w/Value</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="text" value="Value" /></td>
            <td><input type="text" disabled value="Value"></td>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="checkbox" checked /></td>
            <td><input type="checkbox" disabled checked /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><input type="radio" checked /></td>
            <td><input type="radio" disabled checked /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><select><option selected>Value</option></select></td>
            <td><select disabled><option selected>Value</option></select></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td><textarea>Value</textarea></td>
            <td><textarea disabled>Value</textarea></td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>


<p>  <br/>
```</p>

<h3>Results</h3>

<p>You can view <a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/All.html">all the results on one page</a> or see individual ones listed below.</p>

<h4>Windows</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE6.png" title="IE6">IE6</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE7.png" title="IE7">IE7</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE8.png" title="IE8">IE8</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE9.png" title="IE9">IE9</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE10.png" title="IE10">IE10</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Windows-Chrome-17.png" title="Windows - Chrome 17">Chrome 17</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Windows-Safari-5.1.png" title="Windows - Safari 5.1">Safari 5.1</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Windows-Firefox-10.png" title="Windows - Firefox 10">Firefox 10</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Windows-Opera-11.61.png" title="Windows - Opera 11.61">Opera 11.61</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>OS X</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/OSX-Chrome-17.png" title="OSX - Chrome 17">Chrome 17</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/OSX-Safari-5.1.png" title="OSX - Safari 5.1">Safari 5.1</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/OSX-Firefox-11.png" title="OSX - Firefox 11">Firefox 11</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/OSX-Opera-11.61.png" title="OSX - Opera 11.61">Opera 11.61</a></li>
</ul>


<h4>Mobile</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/iOS-5.png" title="iOS 5">iOS 5</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Android-2.3.png" title="Android 2.3">Android 2.3</a></li>
<li><a href="/images/posts/2012-03-17/Opera-Mobile.png" title="Opera Mobile">Opera Mobile</a></li>
</ul>


<h3>Findings</h3>

<p>In general browsers add some combination of <code>opacity</code>, a grayish <code>background-color</code>, and a grayish <code>color</code> to the element to create the disabled effect.  For the most part browsers do a pretty good job making it evident that the fields are disabled.</p>

<p>There are exceptions though.  One glaring issue is the display of disabled text inputs and textareas in IE &lt; 10; when no text is present it's impossible to tell whether the field is disabled.  In Windows, all non-IE browsers simply apply a <code>background-color</code> of <code>#EBEBE4</code> to all disabled elements.  Unfortunately, IE &lt; 10 doesn't do much of anything to designate text inputs and textareas as disabled other than change the color of the text, which, doesn't work out all that well when there's no text present.</p>

<h3>Normalizing IE</h3>

<p>To normalize the display of disabled fields in IE we need to be able to target IE &lt;= 9 with CSS.  Why?  We don't want to override the default styling whenever possible.  As mentioned earlier browsers apply different styling to attempt to match native UI elements.  If you blindly apply a background-color to all disabled elements, you'll do so in Windows, OS X, Linux, iOS, Android, etc… as well as any future devices where it might look horrible, or worse, confuse the user.</p>

<p>So back to selecting IE &lt;= 9.  In my opinion the most elegant way to do this is use <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms537512.aspx">IE's conditional comments</a> to apply classes to the HTML node.  This approach was <a href="http://paulirish.com/2008/conditional-stylesheets-vs-css-hacks-answer-neither/">first proposed by Paul Irish in 2008</a> and is used in the <a href="http://html5boilerplate.com/">HTML5 boilerplate</a>.  There are many variations but in this case we only need to worry about IE &lt;= 9.</p>

<p>``` html Applying a Class to IE &lt;= 9</p>

<!--[if lte IE 9 ]> <html class="lte9"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if (gt IE 9)|!(IE)]><!-->


<p> <html class=""> <!--<![endif]-->
```</p>

<p>Then we can apply the <code>background-color</code> as such:</p>

<p>``` css Normalizing the Disabled Field Display for Windows
.lte9 input[type='text'][disabled], .lte9 textarea[disabled] {</p>

<pre><code>background-color: #EBEBE4;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Alternatively you could use IE's conditional comments to apply these rules directly:</p>

<p>``` html Using IE's Conditional Comments</p>

<!--[if lte IE 9 ]>
    <style>
        input[type='text'][disabled], textarea[disabled] {
            background-color: #EBEBE4;
        }
    </style>
<!--<![endif]-->


<p>```</p>

<p>Either of these approaches will normalize the display of disabled text inputs and textareas on Windows.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-03-17/IE-Before-and-After.png" alt="IE Before and After" /> <!-- http://jsfiddle.net/vCdcr/show/ --></p>

<h3>Normalizing IE6</h3>

<p>The above solution will not affect the display of these elements in IE6 because it does not support CSS attribute selectors.  Therefore, if you're still supporting IE6 and the display of disabled fields is important to your UI you'll need some other sort of hook on the node.  For example a class will work:</p>

<p>``` html IE6 Disabled Field Markup</p>

<!--[if IE 6 ]> <html class="ie6"> <![endif]-->


<!--[if (gt IE 6)|!(IE)]><!-->


<p> <html class=""> <!--<![endif]--></p>

<p>/<em> … </em>/</p>

<p><input type="text" disabled class="disabled" />
<textarea disabled class="disabled">
```</p>

<p>Then you can apply the following CSS:</p>

<p>``` css IE6 Disabled Field Styling
.ie6 input.disabled, .ie6 textarea.disabled {</p>

<pre><code>background-color: #EBEBE4;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h3>Other Issues</h3>

<p>A number of browsers including all OS X browsers except Opera, Android, and iOS do a poor job making textareas appear disabled, in some cases even when text is present.  If your UI contains disabled textareas it's probably worth adding a little bit of opacity to compensate for browsers that don't make it very apparent that you cannot interact with them.</p>

<p>``` css Normalizing Textarea Disabling
textarea:disabled {</p>

<pre><code>opacity: 0.5;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>The effect is subtle but can make a big difference in helping the user to recognize that the field is disabled, especially if multiple textareas are near each other.  Here's an example from Chrome 17 on OS X:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-03-17/OSX-Before-and-After.png" alt="OSX Before and After" /> <!-- http://jsfiddle.net/JpNav/1/show/ --></p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Browsers have default styling for disabled fields that is usually pretty good at visually indicating that the field cannot be interacted with.  In situations where the browser default isn't ideal, custom styling can be applied.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IE7 Attribute Selector Bugs]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/03/08/IE7-Attribute-Selector-Bugs/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/03/08/IE7-Attribute-Selector-Bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The CSS attribute selector allows you to select HTML elements based on their attributes.  For example, take the following markup:</p>

<p>``` html Simple List</p>

<ul>
    <li id="item1"></li>  <!-- #1 -->
    <li id="item2"></li>  <!-- #2 -->
    <li></li>             <!-- #3 -->
</ul>


<p>```</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In a compliant browser, here are some selectors you can use to target these list items.</p>

<p><code>css Selectors to Target the List
li             /* Selects #1, #2, #3 */
li[id]         /* Selects #1, #2 */
li[id=item1]   /* Selects #1 */
li[id='item1'] /* Selects #1, single quotes are valid */
li[id="item2"] /* Selects #1, double quotes are valid too */
li[id^=item]   /* Selects #1, #2, ^ = starts with */
li[id$=1]      /* Selects #1, $ = ends with */
li[id*=item]   /* Selects #1, #2, * = contains */
</code></p>

<h3>Enter IE7</h3>

<p>This is all well and good in most all modern browsers.  Unfortunately IE7 is buggy when handling this selector.  For those of use that are still unlucky enough to be supporting it, I thought it would be nice to have some of these documented.</p>

<h3>DOM Attributes == HTML Attributes?</h3>

<p>Some DOM attributes have different names than the HTML attributes to avoid conflicts with JavaScript reserved words.  Specifically in this case, DOM nodes have <code>htmlFor</code> and <code>className</code> attributes to avoid JavaScript reserved words <code>for</code> and <code>class</code>.</p>

<p>``` html htmlFor and className
<label class="foo" for="name" id="nameLabel">Name:</label>
<input type="text" name="name" id="name" /></p>

<script>
    document.getElementById('nameLabel').for; //undefined
    document.getElementById('nameLabel').htmlFor //'name'
    document.getElementById('nameLabel').class //undefined
    document.getElementById('nameLabel').className //'foo'
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>In IE8+ (and everywhere else for that matter) the following attribute selector will select the label:</p>

<p><code>css Standard Attribute Selector
label[for='name']
</code></p>

<p>In IE7 this won't work.  You'll need to use the incorrect <code>htmlFor</code> attribute:</p>

<p><code>css IE7 for Attribute Selector
label[htmlFor='name']
</code></p>

<p>So if you're still supporting IE7 you'll almost certainly want to include them together:</p>

<p><code>css Combined Selector
label[for='name'], label[htmlFor='name']
</code></p>

<p>Along the same lines, IE7 will incorrectly select attributes based on the className attribute:</p>

<p><code>css IE7 class Attribute Selector
label[className='name']
</code></p>

<p>Fortunately IE7 also supports selecting using <code>class</code>.</p>

<p><code>css class Attribute Selector
label[class='name']
</code></p>

<p>IE8 fixed both of these bugs and selecting for the attributes <code>htmlFor</code> and <code>className</code> no longer work.</p>

<h3>Empty Attributes</h3>

<p>It's impossible to target empty attributes via CSS in IE7.  As an example, let's say you apply a <a href="http://html5doctor.com/html5-custom-data-attributes/">custom HTML5 data attribute</a> to nodes at random throughout the DOM.  Let's say you want to select only the ones that have an empty value, for example the h3 below:</p>

<p>``` html Headings to Select</p>

<h1 data-state="foo">Top Heading<h1>
<h2 data-state="bar">Sub Heading<h2>
<h3 data-state="">Another Heading<h3>
```

You would write this selector and call it a day:

``` css Empty Attribute Selector
[data-state='']
```

Except it won't work in IE7.  There is simply no way to target empty attributes via CSS in IE7.  So how can you replicate this functionality?  For better or worse JavaScript is the only client side option to handle this.

[querySelectorAll](http://caniuse.com/queryselector) isn't supported until IE8, so you need a selector engine to target these nodes.  Here's how you can do it in jQuery:

``` javascript Selecting Nodes with Empty Attribute - jQuery
$('[data-state=""]');
```

If you're using [Dojo](http://dojotoolkit.org) yet another step is necessary.  For whatever reason running…

``` javascript JavaScript Selecting Nodes with Empty Attribute - Dojo
dojo.query('[data-state=""]');
```

…returns not only the nodes with empty attributes, but also all the nodes that don't have the attribute declared at all!  Furthermore, <code>dojo.query('[data-state]')</code> incorrectly doesn't return nodes that have the attribute with an empty value.  So you need the following approach to select the nodes in IE7.

``` javascript Functioning IE7 Approach
dojo.query('*').forEach(function(element) {
    if (dojo.hasAttr(element, 'data-state') && 
      dojo.attr(element, 'data-state') == '') {
        //Safe to finally apply your styling here.
    }
});
```

Note that when using any of the JavaScript based solutions it's recommended to leave the CSS in place.  Yes this is dual maintenance, but it avoids a potential [FOUC](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FOUC).  Fortunately ALL of this nonsense is fixed in IE8.

### Descendant Selector Typos

Let's say you have the following markup.

``` html Sample HTML
<div data-state='active'>
    <p>Some text</p>
</div>
```

…and you want to apply some styling to the paragraph, maybe something like this:

``` css Descendant Selector
div[data-state='active']p {
    color: red;
}
```

Notice how there's no space between the "]" and the "p", that's a syntax error, right?  Correct… except in IE7!  IE7 will incorrectly parse this as if a space were there and change the color of the paragraph to red.

This was also fixed in IE8.

### Summary

We're actually really fortunate that the attribute selector is supported in IE7.  It's a very useful tool to have available and it can help solve a lot of real world issues.  And if you've dropped IE6 support they're finally safe to use.

While support is buggy, the attribute selector does work for the vast majority of use cases.  However, knowing to look out for these bugs can save hours of frustration.  Yet another reason for IE7 to fall off the face of the Earth.  Happy hacking.

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
