<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Forms | TJ VanToll]]></title>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/blog/categories/forms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-20T17:32:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tjvantoll.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[TJ VanToll]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tj.vantoll@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[maxlength Constraint Validation Oddities in Major Browsers]]></title>
    <link href="http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T12:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tjvantoll.com/2012/10/17/maxlength-constraint-validation-oddities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <code>maxlength</code> attribute has been around in browsers for a long time.  When provided, all browsers prevent the user entering a value that exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>For example you cannot type more than 2 characters in the textbox below:</p>

<p><input type="text" maxlength="2"></p>

<h3>Constraint Validation</h3>

<p><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/HTML5/Constraint_validation_">Constraint validation</a> is an HTML5 spec that provides native client side form validation in the browser.  As part of its <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/HTML/Forms_in_HTML#Constraint_Validation_API">API</a>, all <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;textarea&gt;</code> elements have a <code>validity.tooLong</code> property that is <code>true</code> when the length of the <code>value</code> exceeds the <code>maxlength</code>.</p>

<p>But if the browser prevents this, then why does the property exist?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Prefilled value Attribute</h3>

<p>Assume that you're populating the <code>value</code> of form elements from a database and you end up with something like this:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC"&gt;</code></p>

<p>How will the browser handle this?</p>

<p>All browsers will prevent entry of additional characters, but they do not trim excess characters already present.  Additionally, all browsers will allow a form containing the above input to submit.  <em>Note: Opera is the only browser to set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> in this situation.  Despite this, it does not prevent form submission.</em></p>

<p>Why is submission not prevented?  The key is in the <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">specification</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Constraint validation: If an element has a maximum allowed value length, its dirty value flag is true, its value was last changed by a user edit (as opposed to a change made by a script), and the code-unit length of the element's value is greater than the element's maximum allowed value length, then the element is suffering from being too long.</p></blockquote>

<p>The <a href="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/#concept-input-value-dirty-flag">dirty flag</a> essentially means that the user has changed the value of an element.  Therefore, in order to be <code>tooLong</code>, the element must have been edited.</p>

<h3>Actually Triggering tooLong</h3>

<p>So let's take another approach.  What happens if you have the same input:</p>

<p><code>&lt;input type="text" maxlength="1" value="ABC"&gt;</code></p>

<p>...remove one character, then submit?  You can try it for yourself below:</p>

<p><div class="code_example"><h6>Triggering tooLong Errors<a href="/demos/2012-10-17/tooLong.html" target="_blank">Open in New Window</a></h6><iframe style="width: 100%; height: 130px;" frameborder="0" src="/demos/2012-10-17/tooLong.html"></iframe></div></p>

<p>Upon edit IE10 and Chrome will set the <code>validity.tooLong</code> property to <code>true</code> and prevent form submission.  If the user attempts to submit a form after removing the "C" they will see the following in those browsers:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/Chrome.png" title="Chrome" alt="Chrome" />
<img src="/images/posts/2012-10-17/IE10.png" title="IE10" alt="IE10" /></p>

<p>Firefox, Safari, and Opera incorrectly handle this situation and allow the form to be submitted anyways.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
